I’m often asked how I create the
videos you see on NutritionFacts.org.
It’s not just me,
it’s a whole team
of staff and volunteers
who help bring
the videos to life.
It all starts with the research
and every round of new videos,
I read through
every issue
of every English-language
nutrition journal in the world
—so busy folks like
you don’t have to.
And that’s just the
tip of the iceberg.
More than 300,000 nutrition papers
are published every year
in the scientific medical
literature in general
—about 1,000
studies a day.
I typically start with what
I call “anchor” articles.
These are the new studies juicy
enough to center a video around.
Papers that are
groundbreaking, practical,
with actionable information,
and engaging.
Sometimes there’s
trailblazing new science
with hands-on implications,
but unless I can find a way to
make the information interesting—
by adding humor or intrigue,
or solving a mystery—
sometimes, sadly,
it just doesn’t make the cut.
Once I have the anchor paper,
the real work begins:
performing a comprehensive search
of all the available literature
to place that particular
paper in context.
We primarily use
PubMed.gov,
the database of the
National Library of Medicine,
but I have started dabbling with
AI search tools like Elicit.org.
Of course, just because
something is published
in the peer-reviewed medical
literature doesn’t mean it’s true.
There are studies funded by the
National Confectioners Association
that purport to find that
candy is just dandy,
so it always helps to take potential
funding bias into account.
Our article retrieval volunteers
then help download all the articles
we need to read to
analyze and synthesize
the best available balance of
evidence into an annotated script.
Once the scripting work is done,
every script is fact-checked,
then videos are created by the
amazing team at Avo Media.
They’re then reviewed again
by eagle-eyed volunteers
and our fact-
checker and staff,
then are polished,
translated,
and prepped to share
with the world.
We’ve also just brought on
a couple of new researchers
to help update the oldest
videos on NutritionFacts.org.
These videos are outdated,
a little embarrassing,
but the topics are still fresh and
there’s a lot more research available,
so they’ll be getting
an entirely new refresh.
This is all possible
because of our supporters.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships.
It’s strictly noncommercial,
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as
a public service,
as a labor of love.
If NutritionFacts.org has helped you
or your family in any way
and you’d like to do your part
to keep the site going strong,
please consider joining
the thousands of individuals
who support this important
work and make a donation
to the 501(c)(3) nonprofit
that is NutritionFacts.org.